<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="gamedesign.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<GamePitch>
    <meta>
        <title>Diablo Game Pitch</title>
        <description>Diablo is a role-playing game created by Condor, Inc and released in 1996. This
            document, made in 1994, was the original pitch for the game to describe elements such as
            gameplay, marketing, and development.</description>
        <date>1994</date>
        <company>Condor, Inc</company>
        <credits/>
    </meta>
    <document>
        <start_page>
            <img src="images/diablo_start.png" alt="The cover page of the Diablo pitch document."/>
        </start_page>
        <pb/>
        <intro>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">The following is Condor, Inc.'s proposal for a role-playing game, playable on
                PC-compatible computers. Diablo captures familiar fantasy elements within a unique
                structure designed for maximum replayability, expandability, and versatility. Diablo
                fills a neglected niche in the computer game market. As games today substitute
                gameplay with multimedia extravaganzas, and strive toward needless scale and
                complexity, we seek to reinvigorate the hack and slash, feel good gaming audience.
                Emphasis will be on exploration, conflict and character development in a dark quest
                for justice. We hope to produce both a stand-alone game and its expansion disks.
                This initial document will be expanded upon and modified when development is
                initiated.</dev></p>
        </intro>
        
        <section name="Game Design">
            <title>GAME DESIGN</title>
            <title>OVERVIEW:</title>
            <p><GP gtype="genre">Diablo is a role playing game</GP> <GP gtype="mechanic">wherein a player creates a single character and guides
                him through a dungeon in an attempt to find and destroy 'Diablo', the devil himself.
                All the action takes place in an isometric, three-quarter perspective, with
                diamond-shaped, 'square' floor spaces (see diagram). The entire game operates on a
                turn-based system. Using a mouse, the player moves his character from space to
                space, exploring corridors and rooms and engaging in combat. The character faces
                challenges in the form of hostile monsters and traps in his quest to descend deeper
                into the dungeon. Many beneficial weapons and magical items can be acquired and used
                to help on this quest.</GP></p>
            <img src="images/diablo_01.png" alt="Diagram of the floor spaces described above."/>
            <p><GP gtype="mechanic">A player will have the choice of many races and classes for his character. The
                player's character will develop as he defeats monsters and descends to deeper
                dungeon levels. A character will acquire new skills, improve fighting and magic
                abilities, and wield more powerful equipment.</GP></p>
            <p>Forays into the dungeon will be broken up by trips to the town located above. <GP gtype="mechanic">In the
                town, a general store will provide standard equipment and repairs, and will also
                purchase extra equipment from the player. A temple will provide healing for injured
                and sick characters. Training and other facilities may also be available.</GP></p>
            <p><GP gtype="mechanic">The heart of Diablo is the randomly created dungeon. A new dungeon level is generated
                each time a level is entered using our Dynamic Random Level Generation (DRLG)
                System. Rooms, corridors, traps, treasures monsters and stairways will be randomly
                placed, providing anew gaming experience every time Diablo is played. In addition to
                random halls and rooms, larger 'set piece' areas, like a maze or a crypt complex,
                will be predesigned and appear intact in the levels. This system facilitates the
                indusion of puzzles and traps, and helps the addition of thematic elements. Deeper
                levels will contain progressively more difficult creatures and hazards. A
                character's quest ends with the defeat of Diablo, located deep in the dungeon.</GP></p>
            <img src="images/diablo_02.png" alt="Illustration."/>
            <pb/>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">Expandability and replay value are key to Diablo's success. The randomly generated
                dungeon insures new opportunities for exploration as well as unique encounters and
                adventures; no two games will ever be the same. New magic items, creatures, traps,
                as well as complete scenarios can be added to the base game after the initial
                purchase and incorporated directly into the DRLG engine (see discussion of expansion
                packs later in this document). This expandability further adds to continued replay
                value.</dev></p>
            <p><GP gtype="mp">Diablo will support 2-player and multi-player game sessions via modem or network. A
                special 'arena' dungeon will be available for opponents to pit their characters
                against each other. In two-player mode, a user-defined time limit forces players to
                move quickly; if they do not specify a move, they lose their opportunity during that
                turn. As soon as all players register an action, the game progresses, regardless of
                time limit. The ability to play against friends will add to the appeal of the
                expansion packs as players will seek the upper hand versus their friends.</GP></p>
            <title>PLOT AND SETTING:</title>
            <p><setting stype="theme">Diablo is set in a fantastic, medieval world, where sword-and-sorcery-wielding heroes
                battle the forces of darkness. The player's character has just had his life thrown
                upside down when sinister raiders kill his family and destroy his home. Left with
                nothing but a desire for vengeance, the character traces the raiders steps to a
                crypt and an expansive labyrinth below. Gathering up his courage and initial
                weapons, he dives in with fury.</setting></p>
            <img src="images/diablo_03.png" alt="Diagram of how a level is constructed."/>
            <p><setting stype="theme">The world of Diablo will have a dark, evil tone.</setting> <setting stype="place">Initial levels will be set in an
                abandoned Gothic church. A marble mausoleum and progressively darker, dingier crypts
                and catacombs follow. Deeper, natural cave formations lead to supernatural, demonic
                halls, and finally to the opulent chambers of Diablo.</setting></p>
            <p><setting stype="theme">Creatures to be encountered will also follow this sinister theme. The undead will
                predominate in the form of</setting> <NPC role="enemy">skeletons, zombies, ghosts and the like. Deeper levels
                will be populated with lesser demons and chaos-spawn. A sprinkling of 'natural'
                creatures, such as spiders and snakes will add variety.</NPC></p>
            <p><setting stype="theme">Magic items will reflect a religious/demonic theme. For example, a 'Mephistopheles
                Cloak' might allow limited control over lesser evil creatures, while a 'Holy Mace'
                may be just the thing to shatter pesky skeletons.</setting></p>
            <p><setting stype="theme">An open ending will allow for different themes in future sequels, where goblin caves
                or a living fungus world will have to be explored and conquered.</setting> <dev dtype="marketing">The player will
                simply have to purchase an expansion disk to have access to these new worlds.</dev></p>
            <pb/>
            <title>GAMEPLAY:</title>
            <p>A walk-through of an example game session follows:</p>
            <p><GP gtype="mechanic">After starting up the game, the opening cinematic sequence segues into the main menu
                screen. The three options provided are: New Character, Load Character, and Options.
                New Character allows the player to develop a character and start at the beginning.
                Load Character picks up where an existing character last left the game, or allows a
                player to select a pre-generated character to 'quick-start' the game. The Options
                selection gives access to sound and configuration options.</GP></p>
            <p><PC>A player generating a new character is first presented with a choice of race. We plan
                to offer five or six human races Chill people, forest people, etc.) each with
                advantages and disadvantages. After race, the player will select his desired class;
                choosing either a fighter, thief or magician, or possibly sub classes of these.
                Although all characters will be able to use most weapons, and cast some spells,
                different classes will provide special advantages. Fighters will gain extra attacks,
                thieves will move faster and with greater stealth, and magicians will have more
                spells and cast them more powerfully. After making these choices, the computer will
                provide basic statistics for the character in the categories of strength, magical
                aptitude, dexterity and vitality. The player will then be given some discretionary
                points to distribute as he sees fit. Magician characters will pick from
                approximately four 'schools' of magic. There will also be a general school, the
                spells of which are available to all characters. A character will be provided with
                some initial cquipment and gold and then placed in town, where play begins.</PC></p>
            <p><GP gtype="mechanic">If a player had instead chosen Load Character from the main menu and then picked one
                of the pre-generated characters, all of the preceding would be skipped and the
                'quick-start' character would start in town, already equipped.</GP></p>
            <p><setting stype="layout">The town is presented in our isometric view with a main road, a town square, and a
                dozen or so buildings. The player will move his character around by placing the
                mouse-controlled cursor on the 'square' he wishes to walk to and left-clicking.
                Left-clicking on a square will cause the character to move to the selected square by
                the shortest route possible.</setting> <GP gtype="controls">Left-clicking on an item or creature will cause the
                character to move next to it. If already adjacent to an item or creature, a
                left-click causes the character to interact in the appropriate way (trade with a
                shopkeeper, attack a creature, open a chest. etc.). Right clicking will cast the
                readied spell in the indicated location. The arrow keys will scroll the map
                independently of the character.</GP> <GP gtype="mechanic">Moving about the town, the character can visit
                various shops to purchase further equipment, a temple for healing, and his home to
                rest and store extraneous items and gold.</GP></p>
            <img src="images/diablo_04.png" alt="Close-up picture of a demon/the devil."/>
            <pb/>
            <p><setting stype="layout">The fun really begins when the player guides his character down the road and enters
                the abandoned temple (the first level of the dungeon). At this point, the computer
                generates the layout of the first level.</setting></p>
            <p><GP gtype="mechanic">The player can see as much of the dungeon as is visible to the character, determined
                by lighting, line-of-sight, and magical factors. Areas not brightened by light
                sources fade into blackness. Magical 'darkness' can block light sources. Infravision
                can detect heat sources within dark areas (providing red shapes of creatures in the
                distance). As the character moves around, new sections of the dungeon are revealed.
                If a player dicks on a distant square and a creature comes into view in the middle
                of the route, the character will stop to await new orders.</GP></p>
            <p><GP gtype="mechanic">The game runs on a turn-by-turn basis, the player moves, then the opponent(s)
                move(s). Each character and monster may have a certain amount of action points which
                would determine what actions are possible in a given turn. For instance: a fighter
                character turns a corner to suddenly see a skeleton, eight squares away. The player
                left-clicks two squares ahead to close the distance. As the fighter moves forward
                two squares, the skeleton also moves forward two squares and a new skeleton comes
                into view. Moving more carefully, the player clicks one square ahead. The first
                skeleton also moves one square while the second fires an arrow, hitting the fighter.
                Again the player moves forward one square. The first skeleton moves on to the square
                directly in front of the fighter and the second fires another arrow, missing. Now
                the fighter and first skeleton exchange blows, with yet another arrow fired by the
                archer skeleton. Determining that the fighter can't keep sustaining the damage, the
                player clicks six spaces back, in retreat. The first skeleton follows, one space
                behind. The archer skeleton fires each turn until the fighter ducks back around the
                corner.</GP></p>
            <p><GP gtype="mechanic">Assuming the fighter escapes, he will go on to explore the dungeon and finally reach
                the stairs to the next level, whereupon a new level will be generated. If one of
                those arrows ends up killing the fighter, that character will be erased completely
                from the hard drive and the player must start from scratch.</GP></p>
            <img src="images/diablo_05.png" alt="Illustration."/>
            <pb/>
        </section>

        <section name="Marketing">
            <title>MARKETING</title>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">While Diablo shares familiar role-playing elements with other games in this genre,
                its unique structure allows a different marketing strategy, one that could lead to
                sustained, long-term sales.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">There are really two products here: Diablo, which stands on its own, and its
                expansion packs. These packs would consist of one disk and maybe an information card
                in a small package. The disk would contain new elements that are directly
                installable into the base Diablo game. These elements would include: new magic
                items, new creatures, new traps and new level graphics. Expansion disks would all be
                different (or maybe 16 or 32 combinations) and would contain approximately 16 new
                dements in varying degrees of rarity. A sample disk might contain: one rare sword,
                three uncommon magic items, eight common items, two creatures, one trap, and a new
                hallway type.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">A player would buy a new expansion disk or two, go home and install the new data into
                his game. The new elements would be incorporated into the random mix when a new
                level is generated. Perhaps a player's character should have one goodie directly
                placed into his inventory for instant gratification.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">We believe these expansion disks should be priced at around $4.95 with the hope that
                they would be placed near cash registers as point-of-purchase items. Players would
                buy these packs as an afterthought, or maybe in an attempt to collect them all. A
                'collector'-type art card, representing the rare item in a pack, could enhance this
                sense of collectability.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">If Diablo and the expansion packs prove successful, additional expansion pack series
                could be released. Each series would have a theme like Dark Nightmares or Holy
                Avengers.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">This marketing strategy provides many benefits. Expansion packs would add to
                replayability and lengthen the life-span of the product, while providing additional
                and continuous revenues with minimal investment. Point-of-purchase displays would
                serve as advertising, directing people towards Diablo on the shelves. The
                collectible nature would lead to increased sales.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">The unorthodox nature of Diablo and its expansion packs would be unique in the
                computer game world, but it is not without precedent and existing parallels. Magic:
                the Gathering provides some of the inspiration for marketing Diablo. The Expansion
                pack structure would serve as our model. The collectible nature also transfers. The
                tremendous success of Magic is testament to the willingness of players to continue
                to make small additional purchases to revitalize their existing game. In the
                computer gaming world, Diablo and its expansion packs would have no real
                competition. Magic is sold at the register at Electronics Boutique stores; Diablo,
                being a computer game, would fit in nicely.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="marketing">Some precedent can also be found in shareware and demos sold at the register at
                computer stores. The success of speech packs, expansions and sequels for computer
                roll-playing games, provides further evidence that Diablo's expansion packs could be
                successful.</dev></p>
            <pb/>
        </section>

        <section name="Development">
            <title>DEVELOPMENT</title>
            <p><dev dtype="background">Condor plans to spend one year in the development of Diablo. Personnel will consist
                of: one designer; one chief programmer and two junior programmer; two art
                director/artists, one illustrator/sculptor and three pixel artist/illustrators; and
                one music/sound effects person.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="background">Diablo will be art-intensive. We intend for the game to operate in Super VGA mode
                (640x480 pixels). The three-quarter perspective requires eight directions of
                movement, three of which can sometimes be flipped. Each monster will have multiple
                graphic deaths and will require at least 50 frames of animations. We envision
                approximately 16 monsters to start with. The player's character will require many
                more frames to cover different kinds of attacks, casting spells, opening chests,
                etc. Different weapons, armor and clothing types will be reflected in character
                sprites. There will be five or six initial level types as well as an above-ground
                town. Additional art requirements include cinematics, title screens, character
                creation screens and inventory screens.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="background">The programming department's initial task will be the development of a clean,
                intuitive interface. After this, an overall shell structure, the Dynamic Random
                Level Generator, and a sound driver will be implemented in time to allow at least 4
                months of bug testing, and most importantly, play balance.</dev></p>
            <p><dev dtype="background">Music will consist of an opening theme and atmospheric music to accompany game play.
                Sound effects will cover fighting, spell casting, walking and the like.</dev></p>
            <img src="images/diablo_06.png" alt="Illustration of a demonic figure."/>
            <pb/>
            <p><dev dtype="timeline">The initial development schedule proceeds as follows:</dev></p>
            <img src="images/diablo_dev_table.png"
                alt="Table of the development timelinefor Diablo."/>
        </section>
    </document>
</GamePitch>
